The time has come to UV unwrap and
texture our mug. So, we did a little bit
with our icing, our donut, and our
plate. We got most of that for free.
Um it those were very simple objects.
This is a little more complex, so we're
going to have some fun with it. So,
first things first, we need to apply a
texture to it so that we can see the UV
unwrapping and see that it's working
well. So, I'm going to hit N to bring up
my properties and uh I'm using the
polygon add-on and I'm going to apply
the ceramic texture that we're going to
use. So, the free one that we're using
for this tutorial you can find by typing
in donut 5. That'll bring up all the
ones we're going to use in this
tutorial. And uh the one we're using is
this one, this rustic gold uh ceramic
texture. So, I've already downloaded it,
so you'll see uh download. It'll look
like download like that. Um and then
with the mug selected, you want to hit
apply. If the mug isn't selected like
that, you'll see import, which would
just like load it in as a like fake user
material that you could reference. But
anyways, so select the mug and then say
apply. And now we can close that and
let's take a look. Now, you might be
surprised at how well that came in.
Like, the handle's no good, but the rest
of it is semi okay, right? There's some
stretching on the rim and the base, but
like why did that come in okay? So, if
you go to the UV editor here, you can
see we got some islands and this matches
exactly what you would expect if you
created a cylinder. So, when we modeled
this mug, you remember we started with a
cylinder. And that's a primitive object
and Blender automatically UV unwraps the
primitive objects for us. So, everything
that is still a cylinder form
is okay, but everything else that we
created from scratch like this handle
here, it has no idea what to do with it.
So, it's all stretched and all screwed
up. So, basically we have to start from
scratch and um and do this again. But
that's okay, that's the point of this
tutorial to learn how to do UV
unwrapping.
So, as I explained with the icing, the
best way to think about uh UV unwrapping
is to imagine that this object was made
of paper and we have to lay it flat onto
a 2D surface, which is what this is over
here. This is the 3D uh object. This is
the flat surface it's being laid on. So,
it's like we are turning this into paper
and we have to lay it flat. Where would
you put the cuts on this object in order
to make it flat there?
And so, the most obvious place you could
think of if you're looking at doing this
is like I know for sure this handle has
to be separated from the rest of it in
order to start to lay it flat. By the
way, uh before we start, it would
probably help with your um
uh mug selected, in the modifiers,
you've got this little box there that
says uh on cage. So, if it's turned off,
it'll show you like the un subdivided
result around it, but then like parts of
it get hidden by the mesh. So, I usually
turn it on just so that I can see it and
like all the mesh is visible. Just makes
UV unwrapping it uh a little bit easier.
Okay, so the handle needs to be
separated. So, right here is an incision
point, right? So, I'm going to select
these vertices here by holding down
shift and just shift selecting. Then I'm
going to hit control E and then select
mark seam. Now, Blender won't have
updated yet, so this hasn't changed over
here. So, if in order to see that, we
would first have to select the whole
mesh, then go U and then select unwrap.
Or the method that I prefer to do, and I
would suggest you do this too, in your
3D view over here, there's a little
options drop-down at the top there. If
you click that and then select live
unwrap. Now, whenever you do um a seam,
so let's just do another seam here, mark
seam on the same spot, um it will
automatically do that UV unwrap for you.
So, that's really helpful. Um now, it
looks worse. You have to go backwards
before you can go forwards, um but
that's okay. So, we've only got one uh
incision, so let's do another one, the
other half of the handle. So, down here,
I'm going to select these points
like so and then hit control E and then
mark seam. Okay. So, now it has changed.
So, we've got the handle here. Now, if
you want to select just the handle, by
the way, in the 3D viewport, if you just
mouse over that part of the motion of
the the motion the mesh and then hit L,
then in this little um
uh last used box here, if you select
seam, it'll now just select the parts of
the mesh that match that seam. Um by the
way, I should also be in edge select
mode, that would definitely be helpful
um because we're placing seams on edges.
But yeah, if I do that now, uh that
selection, you can clearly see that this
is the part of the mesh, which is this
handle over here. So, it's been
separated, okay? So, we've got like two
parts of the mesh. We've got all of them
this part of the mug, which is this mess
over here, and then we've got this
handle here, which is this part over
here. So, this is like somewhat uh
unwrapped, but again, if this was made
of paper, to lay it flat, we would have
to do another incision. So, when I'm
placing a incision like this, like I
have to place an incision somewhere
here, right? Like here, here, here, or
here. And because a uh a seam generally
makes a seam like a visible line in a
texture that will often not be um like
lined up, that that can look ugly,
right? It's like it's not a good look
for a model. So, often when you're
placing a seam, you put it in a place
that is hidden. So, I mean, it it would
be a really good spot if we had like a
line right down the middle of the mug
there, but next best thing, I'll place
it just to the side there. So, holding
down alt, select that edge. Now, I'm
going to hit control E and then say
seam. And now, look at that. This now
has been pretty well UV unwrapped, okay?
That section there. That's pretty good.
So, now we just have to do the same for
the rest of the mug here. And this is
pretty easy to do. So, it's I mean, you
can tell like one place we would have to
put a cut um would be like the base of
it, like right here
um inside of our mug. So, I'm going to
hold down alt just on this face at the
bottom there and I'm going to hit
control E and I'm going to say seam just
to separate that that single circle
there out by itself. Now, I I need to
put one cut that goes right down the um
right down like here, like this part of
a mesh. Like I need to do a cut right
there. But again, that can create like a
visible like line, so I want to try to
hide it by putting it on like close to
this handle here.
Because also there are other seams here
and it will just kind of help to just
have it on one part of the mesh. Um
because like you you could like move it
and hide it by the camera and stuff like
that. So, it just helps to put it all in
one place. So, holding down alt here, so
alt, click on that. So, it goes all the
way down to there. And then it kind of
stops here on the handle there. So, I'm
going to select this line just holding
down shift. And then I also want to do
it right there. So,
um holding down alt on that and now I'm
going to hit control E and then say mark
seam.
Okay. So, now that's looking a lot more
uh released, right? There's less uh
tension in there, but there is still
this like pinching effect happening at
the bottom there. So, just like in the
middle there, when we selected that and
separated it, I want to select this part
of the mesh, which is underneath the
mug, and I want to unwrap that. Or
sorry, I I place a seam there. By the
way, if you want to like like cuz we
can't really get to that very easily,
if you want to just see an object by
itself, you can hit forward slash. So,
in object mode with the mug selected,
forward slash. And now everything has
vanished. Now, Blender doesn't do a very
good job of showing you that you have
you're just looking at an isolated view
except for at the top there where it
says local. So, there's many times when
I'm using Blender and I think I'm like,
"Where's the rest of my scene?" And then
I remember, "Oh, that's right. I'm in
isolated mode." And you only know
because it says local there. So, you
just have to remember if like you ever
get to that point of like, "Where is
everything? What?" Just forward slash
and it'll bring it back, okay? So,
forward slash, uh there we go. And by
the way, if you don't have a uh forward
slash key, you can go to view um and
then go local view, toggle local view
like that. All right. So, now that I've
done that, I can get underneath my mug
edit mode and I'll select this, say
control E, and then I'm going to say
mark seam. Okay. So, now when we look at
this, you can see we've we've now we
have pretty well successfully UV
unwrapped this, okay? Cuz these points
are now they're they they've been
flattened out. Now, there's there's some
stretching. There's always going to be
some stretching, but as long it is not
like obvious, it's generally okay. But
now what I want to do um is I want to
load in the actual texture that's that's
being viewed here. So, I can see where
this like line is being uh viewed on the
um on the mug there. So, from the
drop-down here, I'm going to select that
base color, this little ceramic mug
here, which by the way was actually
scanned from a real mug um that we uh we
we bought and then scanned around it.
So, this actually matches like what
you'd find in a store. Um so, it's
loaded in there and now with this island
uh which I can select by hitting L like
that, I can now, hitting R, I can start
to rotate and move it around like this.
Okay. So, I'm going to place this. Let's
go right I'm just kind of guessing, but
that is yeah, that's the bottom of my
mesh. So, if you don't know, like you
can go into like face select mode and
just like select a few faces and you can
see them like update over there like
that, which is cool.
Um but yeah, so that's the bottom of the
mug, which is good. And let's get that
like, you know, try and get try and get
a straight line there, okay? And you can
see we can't.
Right? We've got the line like going up
here and then we've got another line
coming down here. And obviously we want
these to meet, but how can we do that,
right? Because the lines are doing that
because this part of the mesh is all the
way uh over here and then the other part
of the mesh is like yeah, much higher
up, right? So, we essentially, in order
to get this to to line up, we need to
make this island here look straight.
Basically like almost like what it was
before when it was uh the default
cylinder view. Now, there are some tools
in Blender that let you like quickly
align like one line, right? So, if I
selected this line here, I could right
click and then I could say align auto
and you could see it would give me a
pretty straight line for for that one
there. The problem is is that it just
does that one line. If I wanted to do
all of it, I would have to do these like
one by one like this. So, Blender really
needs a tool
that would like let this happen like
easily across an entire island. And
although Blender doesn't have this tool,
there is a free extension and it's a
great excuse to talk about extensions in
Blender and how to install them.
But yeah, there's a free one and it's
amazing and so I'm going to show you how
to get it. So, go to edit, then
preferences, then go get extensions. And
with a fresh install, it'll first ask
you do want to let Blender read the
internet cuz it's not going to do that
without your permission. So, say allow
online access. And by the way, you can
change that in the future if you want
inside of system, allow online access.
Anyways, now that you're here in the top
right-hand corner of the get extensions,
there's a little unassuming drop down.
Then click on visit extensions platform.
find them by just going to
extensions.blender.org.
Anyways, so these are all extensions
that
they're not made by Blender. So, they're
not like official, but they are all
free. So, they all have to meet the
criteria of free. I believe there's some
other things in there like it has to I
don't know, probably like safety checks
and things like that. But these just
like expand the capabilities of Blender
by the community. So, the one that we're
looking for is actually this one here,
Moi 3D UV, which you could find by just
I think typing in UV. Weirdly, when I
was typing in Moi 3D,
oh no, that's right. Oh, it's Mio. Oh,
that's why I wasn't finding it. It's Mio
3D. Okay, there you go. I I thought
Blender's search was so bad, but it was
just a Mio 3D, not Moi. All right. Mio
3D UV. Okay. So, this is the extension.
And you might think like I have to
download something, unzip and do that.
No, it's actually really simple. So, all
you do is you grab your browser like
this, just like separate it to make it
like a half window like this.
Then, all you're going to do is
you're going to in the bottom corner of
this little window here where it says
get add-on, you're going to click that.
And then you get this like little
outline box there. And see how your
cursor changes to this little like
crosshair thing? You just click and drag
out from that and then drop it into
Blender. And it'll now say do you want
to install it? And you say yes, I do.
And then that's it.
You can see at the bottom there it says
installed Mio 3D UV. UV. And now in our
UV editor over here in this window, if I
hit N to bring up properties, you can
see I've got a little option here that
says Mio 3D. And look, we've got a bunch
of options that I honestly have not
played with most of them.
Most of the ones I'm looking for are
right at the top here. So, the one that
I use all the time is gridify. Okay, and
look what happens as I click this.
Da da. It does what we're looking for.
It converted that from this like
stretched like kind of view to making it
look actually squarish and and like a
grid. And that is perfect. And now you
can see that line there across the
ceramic is lining up across it. So, that
is absolutely perfect. I have no
complaints. It is it's worked perfectly
well. I do though just want to apply it
to this part of the handle as well
because the same thing would apply to
that. Make sure I do it in face select
mode, so I'll hit L. So, I'm just
selecting the handle by itself. And then
here with this Oh, you can also just do
it on the island itself there like that.
And then go to Mio again and I'm looking
for gridify.
Okay, and there we go.
Great. Now,
you you can position these however you
want. So, you can select an island by
hitting L and then you can like find a
different portion of it. By the way, if
you don't want to see the like cuz you
can't really see the texture under it
very well, sometimes I just disable the
overlay at the top of the screen there.
That will just like disable all the
overlays so you can't see anything on
the mesh there at all.
So, you just have to remember that it's
doing that. But when I've got that, now
I can like move things around
and I can see them visualized on the
actual mesh there, which is helpful. So,
if I wanted to be like a larger looking
texture, I could make it smaller, right?
That's a kind of a look. Or I could make
it bigger and I'll probably make it like
somewhere in between.
About
about there I think actually looks kind
of good.
Actually, yeah, basically filling the
space like that from like left to right,
which is nice. And then for the handle,
I need to also resize that. So, I'm
going to select this part of the handle.
And by the way, you'll notice as you
slide it off the screen there, it
doesn't matter where it is because it's
just going to be tiled. Okay? So, that
texture is just tiling all the way to
the left and to the right and and above
it.
So, yeah. So, I can position this
wherever I want like so.
Now, you can see here this little empty
patch here, right? This is one part of
the handle cut, right? It's that
section. And then this section here
would be this right here. So, if you
actually wanted to line it up to be
perfect and also get the texture, it's
it's called like matching the texel
density across the islands.
But yeah, you could like scale this down
to be
like roughly the same portion, like the
same part of the mesh if you want to.
There's still like this extra stretching
and stuff in there.
The other thing I sometimes do is like I
look at the size of a square like this
and then I go like what is the size of
the square over here? And it's like, all
right, that's pretty close, but I can
see it needs to be stretched like
further this way, right? Cuz this is
more rectangular than this. This is more
kind of squarish. So, I'm going to
select this whole island and I could hit
S and then Y
like so.
So, till they're kind of kind of the
same size like that. And then just to
make them fit, I would scale that down
again.
And there you go. And now I'm just going
to move that up a little bit just so
that this part here
of my my texture. I want it to kind of
line up there. I don't even know
actually if this is physically possible.
Maybe somebody who works in pottery will
tell me. But like see how it looks like
it's kind of like dipped in something? I
don't even know if that's like something
that is like painted or like branded or
something. Like can it go halfway up the
handle as well?
I'm assuming it did. Maybe I thought it
was like dipped in something, but that
could be like this could be a completely
implausible mug is all I'm saying.
But that that's how it is in 3D like you
have artists that have like never done
engineering before and they design a
robot. And then like everyone's like,
yeah, that looks cool. And then like all
the people in engineering are like, you
know, that's never going to fly, you
know?
But that's that's fine. It's part of the
part of the fun of it.
Okay, now there's there's a lot of
stretching going on right here. And
that's because this gridify thing as
good as as good as it is, you could see
that this part, right? It's really like
shrunk it in there and it's made it a
really thin line. So, all I'm going to
do is I'm going to go into edge select
mode by hitting two. I'm going to select
that edge. Oh, okay, I can't select that
edge very well. I'll just shift select
them one by one like that. And then I'm
just going to pull it up just to add
more detail there like so. And I think
it is also like
stretched a little bit because it's kind
of like wrapped around it and it's kind
of like peeling outwards a little bit. I
think it works a little bit better if
you also scale that part out a little
more. So, I'm just scaling out that
line. And you can see that has now
blended in pretty seamlessly. Like
that's about I mean, it's a little messy
there, but it's about as good as it
would get on that. That's that's pretty
good. And then I'll just do the same for
the bottom part here. So, I'll select
these edges.
Actually, no, I'll do it over here. You
can see you get both parts of it, right?
Cuz that line there exists across two
islands, right? This island and then
this island here. So, anyways, I'll
select this in the editor here.
And then I'm going to pull it down to
give me more data. And then I'm going to
scale it out a little bit as well.
And look at that. That's pretty good.
We've got a pretty seamless looking
result.
I mean, and honestly, that's that's
about as good as it gets. And by the
way, I I should have said like it
doesn't actually matter that the UV
islands are overlapping here. But it
does matter if you were to be painting
onto this.
And the reason that that that makes a
difference is like you can imagine if
you were doing a paintbrush and you had
painted parts of the mesh here and like
one part was for the handle and this
part was for that. If you had islands
that were overlapping each other, then
you would have like different parts of
the painting like appearing twice across
it. So, there's kind of like two styles
to UV unwrapping. This is the simplest
one, which is just like if you've got an
image that you've got off the internet
or a texture or whatever that's just
being tiled across it or even not tiled.
Like it doesn't matter if things are
overlapping because, you know, the
texture is different enough your eyes
not going to spot it. But if it's
painted, yes, they do have to be
separate parts. And another thing as
well, if you're UV unwrapping for a game
asset, it's even more complex because
all the islands have to be separated,
but there's also like margin because
like in games you develop like multiple
versions of a mesh at different
resolutions, then there's different
texture resolutions. So, you have to
create like big margins. And it gets all
like complicated. It it's like a
completely separate thing. So, if you
wanted to texture for games, you should
probably look at like game texturing
type tutorials if you really wanted to
go into that. But anyways, the rest of
it is fine. Like that part of it, all
this like stretching in here if you
wanted to fix that, you could. It
doesn't matter cuz we're going to put
some like coffee foam along the top
there. The base of it doesn't matter cuz
we're not going to see it.
So, yeah.
But that's that's also the the the thing
to consider is like, you know, when
people are like on Twitter and they're
like, look at this model. Look how
terrible it is. It's like, yeah, it
might be for a purpose like this. It's
designed to be viewed from above, and
that's all it needs to do. Like, if
you've like pulled it apart and it's
like, "How terrible does it look?" It's
like, "Yeah, the camera was never going
to go in there or under there, so that's
why it doesn't matter."
Anyways, all right. So, the mug is
pretty good. The only thing I'll do is
I'm going to go to my material over
here. Uh actually, oh, sorry. I'll go to
my shading tab at the top there, so that
I can access the nodes here, and I'll
just make a few tweaks to it. Just like
before
when I mentioned these maps here, like,
this is going to give you the physically
accurate um
data from the actual ceramic that we
scanned, right? And it's like color
calibrated and everything like that. Um
but sometimes you want artistic control,
and I want this to look shinier. This is
a little dull for me. So, I'm going to
disconnect my roughness here, and then
I'm just going to play with this slider.
Like so. So, I've still got the bumps,
so like most of the detail that I want
is still there, but like I don't need I
don't need um I don't need to look as
dull as it was, so that is pretty good.
I also don't need the metallic shader,
like that's just superfluous. Um there's
another one here, ORM. Oh, sorry, not
ORM.
Uh ambient occlusion or AO. This is
another one which is completely
unnecessary. Um it's just for like
crevices of information, but this is
like flat ceramic, so there's no
crevices. Um we have to provide it like
standardized for all of our materials,
so they're all uniform, but a lot of
materials just don't need it. So, in a
case like this, um I just don't want the
AO, like this map here. So, I could just
like disconnect that. Or actually, if
you want to delete something like this
and you want it to retain its
connection, rather than just deleting
it, cuz then you have to manually
connect it, um if instead,
if you hit control X, it will delete it
and retain its connection. So, that's
just a little tip there for you.
Okay, great. So, now let's go back to my
layout mode over here. Let's have a look
at it without lighting, and that is
pretty good.
Now, the only thing I would change
though, looking at this, is
this concrete is mighty pale. It doesn't
look very good. It doesn't look very
luxury like a like a cafe, like a high
highfalutin, "Ooh, look at me. I'm
paying $9 for a coffee. Aren't I fancy?"
Doesn't look like that, right? It looks
like dusty, like a workman floor. So, we
can adjust this by going to the shame
touch. This is a great excuse to go a
little a little into the nodes, right?
So, this is the one that we actually
manually set up, so it's you know, it's
pretty clean. We just got a base color,
and we've got a normal map, right? But
between here and here, where it
connects, we can adjust the color of
this, and I'm going to show you how
simple you can you can completely
transform the look of a texture.
So, if I hit
uh shift A or just go to add at the top
there, then go to color, and there's a
bunch of different color options like
brightness and contrast. I wouldn't use
that. That's like a
like what is brightness? What is
contrast? There's a whole like color
debate and things. Color ramp can be
useful if you just want to like convert
something to like your own set of
colors. Uh hue saturation value, we use
that. The one I'm looking for though is
RGB curves. So, if I drop this in here,
this will give me if you're familiar
with RGB curves from like Photoshop or
DaVinci or anything like that, this will
let you do like an S-log uh kind of
curve. So, essentially,
this data at the bottom here, this is
your uh your dark dark tones. Uh this
would be your midtones. This would be
your highlights, and this is like your
clipped like highlights at the top
there. But you can see if I make this
look like a like a ramp like this, it
starts to look more contrasted,
right? And I pull it all the way down. I
can like really transform this and make
it look really contrasted. Look at how
different that looks already, right?
From just this one little thing, you
wouldn't imagine you could convert it
like this, but that's a simple thing,
and it's already looking good. And then
I want to bring out some of the whites
as well, so I can just add at the top
here just a little curve that goes the
other way, so it kind of exaggerates
some of those whites. Okay?
Great. That's pretty good. But now, the
other thing is is like because I've like
crunched it and made it a little more
contrasty, it's also brought out some of
the colors, which are looking a little
like yellowy green, which is a little
unappealing. Kind of like this table
would be like a little moldy, not great.
So, instead, um to improve it, I can add
another node. As I mentioned, I use this
one a lot, hue saturation value. So, if
I drop this in and I drop it in here,
you could also put it before the the
curves or after, it doesn't really
matter. Um and then I would I just want
to drop the saturation here, and watch
this. Watch how completely transform
this becomes.
Woohoo! Look at that.
Doesn't that look nice?
I think it looks nice.
It's like and you can turn off these
nodes, by the way, like temporarily. If
you want to mute something, it's M. M
for mute.
And you can select that and mute it. So,
this is what we started with, and then
just with two nodes, we converted this
pale looking concrete
into this,
which is crazy.
Pretty cool. Anyways, so that's that's
nice. And then, you know, you can
obviously play with the the roughness
and stuff, and we'll get to that when we
get to the
the lighting a little bit more.
Um but that is looking good. Oh, the
other thing, of course, we need to add
is our coffee foam. And this one is
super easy, and it's another chance to
talk about um another type of texture
which you can find on sites like
Polygon. Um but we need to add coffee
foam to this. And um to do that, we need
to start with an object that is going to
obviously fill the top of this. And
obviously, you know, we could go in here
and we could like add in a circle and do
that kind of thing, but it's also smart
to think about like, "How can I save
time by reusing part of my mesh that I
already have?" So, I already know the
exact size that the the foam to fit my
mug, because I already have a mug here
with a circle in it, right? Look at this
line.
That is a circle. If I could just take
that and make it a new object, I can use
it. So, to do that, I can select that
line and then hit shift D, right? I've
got my circle now. Then I want to hit
escape, okay?
So, it's now just brought it back to
where it was, and now I'm going to hit
P. P is how you separate something to a
new object. So, you're separating part
of the the mesh.
So, now I'm going to hit selection
like that. And now, if I go over to my
uh outliner here, we should see two
mugs. So, this is my original mug, and
then this is my mug.001,
okay? So, I'm going to call this my foam
like that.
And now,
I'm going to go into edit mode.
Uh let's put it in edit mode.
All right, and I'll turn off the uh that
little view there, so that I can just
see
Where is it? Hold on a second.
Huh? All right. Okay. So, you have to go
into uh wireframe mode in order to see
it there, but yeah, that is my my
circle. Um and actually, yeah, I should
just be in my layout mode, shouldn't I?
Not in shading. I should be in layout.
So, I'm going to go here. Let's do the
same thing. Wireframe mode. Okay.
So, this circle obviously isn't being
rendered because there's no face on it.
So, if I go into here into wireframe, um
I need to create a face on that, and I
can do that by hitting F, okay? So, I've
now got a face, and it's completely flat
across it. And this is okay, and this
would yeah, it would work for most
things, but there is a small detail that
you notice when you look at like like if
you've got a if you've got a coffee on
your desk right now, if you have a look
at it, where the coffee like where the
water meets the actual edge there,
there's like surface tension, and it
actually rises up against the edge
there. And you might think that is like
a negligible detail, but that line there
always catches light. And when it's
missing, the eye goes like, "That looks
fake." So, it's a very small thing, but
we can add that line in here very
simply. So, in edit mode, going back in
wireframe mode, so with our solid face
here, I can create an inset. Okay, have
we talked about insets? I'm trying to
think.
Yeah, we did a little ins Yeah, we've
done some insets. Okay. But yeah, you
hit I, okay? To do an inset. Um and
that's just like creating a line like
that goes all the way around that one
single face there. And now, I can put it
like Yeah, let's go right there.
And then, right underneath it, I'm just
going to Sorry, yeah, right here. I'm
going to hit G and then Z to bring it
down like so.
And then now, let's have a look at it in
solid view mode.
And look at that. So, I've now got it,
and it's pretty good. I might just do
another inset cuz it's got this like
crimped kind of effect there, so I'm
going to hit I just so that it's not so
noticeable on that portion.
Okay, nice. And now, all the all I need
to do is right click it and say shade
smooth. So, now I've got a little raised
edge to it.
Excellent. By the way, quick little
opportunity to talk about
something like it's kind of hard to see
that raised edge there. It is there, but
it's just like the lighting doesn't
really make it
visible. So, sometimes when you're
modeling, it can be helpful to change
the way things are displayed here. So,
there's a really powerful tool in the
top right-hand corner.
Um the default lighting is studio. If
you go to matcap and then click this
ball here, you've got all these options,
which can show you different views. Um
it's actually how I create some of my 3D
my YouTube thumbnails, cuz some of these
look really beautiful. But like you can
see that's so much more useful um for
seeing
what that edge actually looks like there
on that. Um and there's some like this
which are designed to like show you
where there is like artifacting on your
mesh, cuz it'll reveal
um problems with the mesh that you
otherwise might not have seen.
Um and these are new in Blender 5.0. Um
they redid the matcaps, I should say. Um
but anyways, it's cool. It's nice to
have, but we don't really need it. Okay,
so to give it a coffee foam texture, I'm
going to hit N to bring up my properties
over here, and then I'm going to
download my coffee foam atlas texture.
So, let's hit download, and then with it
selected, I'm going to hit apply. If I
go into render view mode, it should look
like that.
Let's go to the uh UV editor, okay, cuz
I don't think it's been UV unwrapped.
Nope, it has not been UV unwrapped. And
then I'm going to go into top view mode
by hitting seven, and then I'm just
going to say U and then go unwrap angle
based, like that. Now, I want to see
this on my coffee atlas, cuz this is a
special texture, and it's called an
atlas texture. I'll show you what it
looks like.
Okay, so it looks like this. And this is
a bunch of different coffee foams that
you get to choose from. And so with in
edit mode, with this UV uh selection
here, I need to scale this down
over the coffee foams,
and then I just move them around
to the one that I want. Like, what sort
of coffee foam do you want
on your mug?
Right? Like some bubbles.
Uh funny story with the coffee foam,
like every uh the annoying thing about
having like an asset company is every
subject there is it's like trying to
reinvent the wheel, cuz like how do you
create a texture for coffee foam?
Um because you could photograph it, but
then how do you get the detail like the
bubbles, right? Cuz like bubbles, you
can't get the shape of those bubbles.
Like So, we use like substance first.
Like we hired somebody to make some very
expensive
substance materials. I can't remember
what we paid, $2,000 or something like
that. Um but then there are some things
which are just like really hard to do
procedurally with substance. Substance,
if you don't know, it's like a
completely uh separate texturing
software. Um it's very complicated, all
node based. Um but we got somebody like
super skilled, and it's just really hard
to get the detail of bubbles here. Um
and then we had a guy on our team who
was like on Saturday, he's like, "Look,
I don't know if this going to work, but
I just I took some photographs of some
coffee, and then I took it into
Substance Painter, and I manually placed
the bubbles so that they all have the
exact like shape of the detail,
and it worked. And
it was like
sometimes the cheap and easy I mean, it
was, you know, it still took him a day
to do it, but like it actually it
actually works. Um
but yeah, it's kind of like we just have
to guess what's actually going to work
for it, um and just kind of wing it. But
anyways, you can pick whichever one you
want. I can't really even remember which
one I used for the Oh, yeah, it was that
one at the top. That was what I used in
the animation. Um but I'll let you
choose, cuz you've got nine choices to
choose from. Some of them are frothy,
espresso looking, but that was the one
that I went with. Now, if you go to
render it, you might find I'm not
actually seeing it on this one. First
time I brought it in, there was um
uh in the shading tab, because it treats
this as like alpha.
Yeah, so it I I thought it treated that
as like alpha. We don't really need that
alpha. Like alpha will make something
like transparent, but there's nothing
transparent on this. So, if you see any
like see-through stuff stuff or
whatever, you might just have to
disconnect that. I don't need metallic.
I do need the roughness, the base, and
the normal, so I'm going to keep those.
And I also don't need my AO, so I'm
going to uh control X on that, and there
we go. So, that was the very basics of
UV unwrapping. Uh if you want to go
further and learn how to UV unwrap
something a lot more detailed with hard
flat surfaces, placing the cuts in the
right spots to avoid stretching, um as
well as how to UV unwrap something
smooth and organic, um and then texture
it using procedural textures, painted
textures, that's all covered in my
course called the Beginners Academy,
which I designed for people who have
finished this tutorial uh and want to go
further. So, if you're interested in
that, the link for that is beneath this
video.
Otherwise, let's continue on with
finalizing our donut scene by clicking
this video on screen.